[tribal music]
[Mitch] Hawaii...
It’s always been my place to go
for excitement, relaxation and fun.
[tribal music continues]
But for me, right now,
it’s a place of solitude.
Empty beaches, a place
where I can be alone.
I’m here on a personal search.
Something I just realized I had lost.
Finding it isn’t going to be easy.
But, it takes some time.
Probably some pain.
And a little, or a lot, of heartache.
But, if I'm lucky,
if I'm real lucky,
I’ll find what I’m looking for.
I’ll find me.
[Hina] Come on, Eric, let's go!
[Mother] Let's go, kids!
Hey, come on, you guys!
[Eric] The waves are so big.
-Come on, Eric, let's go!
-Let's go!
[Eric] Wow!
[Hina screams]
Hey, kids, wait for us, now.
Don’t go by the rocks!
[Hina screams]
[Eric] Yeah!
[suspense music]
[laughter]
-[Mother] The kids!
-Hina! Eric!
[Father] I'm coming!
[Mother] Hina!
[Mother] Hold on!
[coughing and gasping]
[Hina screaming] Help!
[Father] Come, guys, here! Eric!
[Father] Eric!
Help!
[Hina] Help! Daddy, help!
[Father] Help!
[gasping]
[Father] Hina, Hina!
I'm coming. I'm coming!
[Hina] Help! Daddy, help!
[Mother gasping and moaning]
-Are you alright?
-Ah... yeah.
[Hina coughing]
[Father] Eric!
Eric!
Hang on, I got you.
Just relax. Let me do the work.
Let me do the work! I got you.
[Mitch] Stay with your daughter.
You’re doing great.
Hang on! I’ll be back.
-Dad! Daddy, where are you? Help me!
-Hina!
-Stay with your mother.
-Oh, baby!
Hina!
Get my daughter!
-Can you swim to shore?
-I have to find my daughter.
I’ll get her, but I can’t handle both
of you. Tell me you can swim to shore.
-Yes.
-Then do it. Trust me. I’ll get her.
She'll be alright. Go!
[suspense music]
[suspense music continues]
[moans and gasps]
[dramatic music]
[Mother] Oh! Oh, Hina! Oh, no!
[Mother] No...
Oh, man, she’s not breathing.
Okay, give me some space. I’m a lifeguard.
[Mother moans]
[Father] Oh, come on, honey.
Come on, honey, breathe now.
One, and two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven,
twelve, thirteen, fourteen, fifteen.
[ambulance siren]
[Hina coughs]
[man] Okay, c’mon, give us some room.
We’re M.I.C.T.’s.
Okay, buddy, we got her.
[Mitch] I got her breathing,
but she’s not conscious.
[paramedic] She’s not breathing.
Not responding.
[Father] Come on, honey. Hang in, hang in.
[Mother] Oh, baby...
[paramedic] Wahiawa Hospital, we’ve got
a young girl, unconscious, not responding.
[paramedics chatting]
[paramedic] Roger, we’re coming in.
Code three.
Get a respirator,
get her on a stretcher.
[Father] Just hang in. Oh, God, Hina.
Hey, where did he go?
[Father] I wanted to thank him.
He saved her.
He saved all of us.
[opening theme song]
[birds chirping]
Hey.
So much has happened, Rock.
Father passed away.
Hobie’s gone off to college.
I hardly talk to him anymore.
Mom has Alzheimer’s.
She doesn’t even know who I am.
I still think about my ex-wife.
I’m just burned out.
-You're tired.
-No, there’s more to it than that.
I’ve lost my confidence.
I don’t think I should
be on the beach anymore.
Mitch...
You pulled a family of four
out of killer surf, by yourself.
Just because of you,
they’re still alive.
The girl’s in the hospital.
-She's alive.
-She’s in intensive care.
She hasn’t regained consciousness.
That’s because of me.
A couple of years ago,
I would have saved them all.
Mitch... three times in that surf
would take it out of anyone.
It wasn’t about being tired.
I’ve been tired before.
I made mistakes, Rock.
I thought the little girl was caught in
a rip current, she was in the lava tube.
I spent most of my time
looking in the wrong place.
Look at that rock face.
Look at the way
the waves break along it.
Caves, lava tubes, rip tides.
That’s why the family was sucked in.
How were you to know?
You can tell that by just looking at it?
Experience. This is my turf.
-Wish I had known that.
-I wish I would've been here to tell you.
Me too.
[beeping]
[sad music]
[sad music continues]
-Rock!
-Hey, Mitch.
Looking good, bro. What,
do you want to work my tower?
No, no, no. I want to talk to you
about something. Got a minute?
Sure. Dave, man, cover my tower.
[Mitch] The incident
with that little girl really affected me.
-Ignorance kills, right?
-[Rock] Every day.
[Mitch] Okay. Now, as lifeguards,
how do we learn?
We learn from personal experience,
we also learn by talking to each other.
Rock, the idea of the center
is a place where lifeguards
come from all over the world
and they share ideas,
personal experiences, rescue techniques.
They learn from each other.
You know, if I'd talked to you before
that family was swept off the rocks,
I would've handled
that rescue differently.
Is this purging off some guilt trip?
What difference does it make
the motivation here?
-It’s about saving lives, okay?
-Okay, don’t bite my head off.
Rock, in Australia, last year,
they lost 100 swimmers due to drowning.
In Japan, in one weekend alone,
they lost 80 people.
That may not have happened if
the lifeguards had talked to each other.
All I’m saying is
maybe a little of what you know,
combined with a little of what I know
could help solve the problem.
I thought about going back to L.A.
and setting it up there,
but L.A.’s not the right spot.
Conditions are too constant.
To train right
in every possible situation:
reef breaks, shore breaks,
big surf, flat surf, cliffs.
-Hawaii.
-Yeah. Oahu.
The North Shore.
We need a team, Rock.
The team should be trained here,
familiar with all kinds of conditions.
Well, we could help you with that.
Who else would you involve?
Eventually, every lifeguard
in every country in the world.
Bring what they do best.
We take L.A., for example.
What do you admire most
about L.A. lifeguards?
Organization. You guys
have put together a great system.
-What about Hawaii?
-We have some great individual water men.
You guys also know big surf and
you’ve also perfected the jet ski rescues.
I like the Aussies. And
they use those Rubber Boats.
They’re competitive.
They'd bring an edge to training.
They hate to lose.
-South Africans are pretty innovative.
-Germany and Brazil got lots to offer.
But we’re getting too big here.
We need one team. A small group
of elite individuals.
You know, Mitch, I’d really like
to see you make this work.
I’ll make it work.
All I gotta do is think of that little
girl in the hospital,
fighting for her life,
because of my ignorance of conditions.
I won’t let that happen again.
[Mitch] If I’m going to put together
this team, I gotta get somebody I know.
Go back to California.
Get two of the best.
JD Darias and...
Jessie Owens.
You’re drifting, Jessie. Concentrate.
Just don’t stroke. Focus!
Agh! I am focused!
Now you are, but you weren’t.
[sighs] I hate you, JD!
Hate the water that’s in front of you.
Hate your own mediocrity. Hate losing.
But me? Me, you gotta love.
Hey! Why do I ‘gotta’?
Because...
Jessie, my love.
I am making you better.
[moans in frustration]
So, what do I tell Mitch?
Tell him we can’t go.
I’m not going to stop training, JD.
No distractions, remember?
That was the rule.
No excuses.
I’ve got to win this rotten race.
Hello?
Jessie. The best triathlon
on the planet is, where?
That’s right. Maui. And where is Maui?
That’s right. Hawaii.
And where does Mitch want us to go?
[laughing] Okay, okay!
I promise I will have you ready.
Okay, JD.
If you promise, then I’ll go.
Great! You know,
there’s something else about Maui.
Yeah? What's that?
It is, ah, the number one honeymoon
destination spot in the world.
Is that a proposal?
I don't know... is it?
Sure sounds like one to me.
Well, what do you think?
I think that I need to do this race,
but then anything’s possible.
[both laugh]
[Mitch] You know, I love the Aussies.
Competitive, confident.
Allie Reese, helicopter pilot
and has mastered the techniques
of using the inflatable Rubber Boat
for surf rescues.
So I sent her a plane ticket.
What could this be?
An invitation.
[sighs]
Wow. A classic, huh?
Oldie but goodie.
Hey, Rock, what do you know
about this guy, Sean Monroe?
You know him.
He used to be with L.A. County.
Yeah, I know. He’s on Kauai, now.
What do the local guys say about him?
-Good reputation?
-Yeah. Tough.
A loner. Learns quick, though. Why?
I’m thinking about choosing him
to run the training center.
-Sean Monroe?
-What do you think?
One thing’s for sure.
He knows these waters.
[people screaming]
[suspense music]
[Mitch] Sean Monroe works
some of the toughest,
most dangerous beaches
on the planet.
The Na Pali Coast.
This is my choice of team leader.
He’s the master of Risk Management.
He anticipates. He’s passionate.
Dedicated. Determined. He saves lives.
[suspense music continues]
[woman] Help! Help! Over here!
[people screaming]
-[man] Help!
-[woman] Here!
Relax. Just let me do the work.
[people gasping and moaning]
[Sean] Get that over here.
Are you alright, man?
You okay?
[woman] Thank you!
Reach for me.
[Sean] Here.
[Sean] Hey! Anybody left?
[lifeguard] We got them all!
[lifeguard] Eight went in. Eight came out.
Alright, it’s clear.
Let’s get out of here.
You guys are pretty lucky.
[Mitch on radio] Sean Monroe.
[Sean] Mitch Buchannon,
how the hell did you find me here?
A what?
A lifeguard training center?
I don’t know, Mitch.
It sounds like a lot of yack.
Yeah, yeah, I’ll check it out.
But you know me.
If it gets boring, I’m gone.
-Hey.
I just came by to tell you
that I’m really sorry.
I know I promised I’d save her.
You did. She’s alive!
She should be home, not in a coma.
Have they updated her condition
or told you anything?
[Father] Yeah, to... to wait,
to be patient,
to pray.
Do you want to go in and see her?
[monitor beeping]
[Mitch] Hey...
I spent so much time
looking for her in a rip
and she was in the lava tube.
I wasted so much time
looking in the wrong place.
Don't mourn her.
What?
You are mourning like she’s dead.
She’s not.
She’s alive.
She’s gonna be twelve.
[Father] We’re gonna have a party.
You're invited.
I'll be there.
Good. When you come,
you come to celebrate.
Yeah, I will.
Then you will be welcome.
I don’t even know her name.
Hina.
Her name is Hina.
Hey, Hina.
[woman] Aloha. On behalf of all of us
at Hawaiian Airlines,
we wanted to thank you for choosing
to fly with us today.
Welcome to Hawaii. Mahalo.
-I think this is mine.
-It's not.
Look, kid, a lot of bags look alike.
-You wanna turn it loose?
-Do you have your claim check?
-No, do you?
-Of course I do.
It's right here.
It... it's not mine.
-Sorry.
-No problem.
You’re not going to get out
without a claim check.
Yeah, I will.
Thank you for coming to Dollar.
-Have a nice day.
-[man] Thank you.
Welcome to Hawaii and Dollar Rent A Car.
Yeah, I was told to come here
and pick up a car,
under the name Baywatch Hawaii.
-Okay, under Mister...?
-Jason. No Mister.
Just Jason.
Jason.
Jason...
Here it is. All I need is your signature.
So what did I get?
A van.
A van?
Please, I’m a single guy.
My first time in Hawaii.
Sunshine, blue skies.
Come on, help me out here.
[upbeat music]
-[Allie] Baywatch.
-That's right.
Hi, I’m Allie Reese.
I'm in love.
Oh, ah, what was your name?
Jason.
-And how old are you, Jason?
-Nineteen.
Ah, that’s too young.
I'll get older.
[laughing] I don’t think
I can wait that long.
You have to.
This old crone in Port Arthur
said I’d marry the most beautiful
woman in the world.
[Jessie] Allie? Oh, my God!
I can't believe it!
How are you?
It’s so good to see you. How is everyone?
How’s Cody and Alex?
Good. Just guarding’ the beaches of L.A.
JD, this is Allie Reese.
We met in Australia.
-Nice to meet you.
-Heard a lot about you.
Oh, and this is, um, Jason.
I didn’t catch his last name.
Jason's enough.
-Hey. Jessie Owens.
-Pleasure.
-You coming with us?
-No. You’re coming with me.
[upbeat music]
Jessie!
Jessie?
Jessie, let's...
go... oh.
Jessie’s not here.
Yeah, right, ah...
You, you, you see,
there’s a meeting, and...
Um...
Kekoa Tanaka.
-Kekoa Tanaka?
-That's my name.
Oh, right! JD.
Hi.
There’s a meeting, JD. You don't
wanna be late on your first day.
Right.
-Hey!
-Hey, you, muah!
-Where you been?
-I’ve been looking for you.
-Yeah?
-Yeah.
Hey! Are you alright?
No! Never better.
-Yeah?
-Yeah.
Who's that?
Oh, ah, one of the Hawaiian lifeguards.
Her name’s, ah, Kekoa Tanaka,
or something like that.
She’s got an interesting look, huh?
She’s pretty.
-You think so?
-Yeah, don't you?
Yeah... yeah.
She’s got an interesting look.
JD, it’s okay to think
that other girls are pretty.
It’s when you act like they’re not
that I get concerned.
Jessie, what,
are we going to argue about this?
I mean, she’s a pretty girl.
She’s a knock out.
She’s Miss All Everything, okay?
Okay.
C’mon, I found a place to do laps.
There’s no pool, but there’s
some quiet water across the way.
Hey, who’s the hapa haole?
That’s the kid Roger Lorenz
sent us from Galveston.
Says he’s a prodigy.
Listen, I’m going to go find Mitch.
Say, Cuz.
The name’s Jason.
And I ain’t ‘hapa’ anything.
Jason. I’m Kai Colburn.
And hapa’s not an insult,
it means half, or part.
Almost everyone in Hawaii is hapa.
That’s you. Me? I’m me.
One thing, one piece,
one person, all together.
Didn’t mean to hurt your feelings.
-You didn't.
-Say, Jason.
Yeah, Kai?
I’m sure they told you in Texas
about all the sharks we have here.
Well, don’t be afraid.
It’s not as bad as you’ve heard.
-You trying to get in my head?
-I don’t know. Can I?
I don’t know. Can you?
So, how do you want to handle this first
meeting? Who is gonna say what?
I want you to do it all.
Mitch, this is your show.
You put the money together, set it all up.
I’m basically just kitchen help.
Sean, I’ve got responsibilities
back in L.A.
I’m sure you can handle it.
I’ll be around for advice and counsel.
Alright. I won’t let you down.
I know you won't.
That’s why I picked you.
I’m Sean Monroe.
Ten years with L.A. County.
Five years here in Hawaii.
We’re going to be setting up
a lifeguard training center here.
But before we can invite other lifeguards,
every member of this team
must know these waters.
The beaches, the surf, the rips,
every kind of condition.
So, we will train.
And we will train
‘til every member of this team
is proficient with the equipment
and the area.
The training will be difficult
and dangerous.
Now, Mitch picked me to head up this team.
He picked you to be a part of this team.
I'll say that again.
He picked you. I didn’t.
So, I’m assuming you must all
be pretty good, huh?
Strong swimmers, great lifeguards.
Heroes where you’re from, right?
Well, I got news for you,
this is the North Shore of Oahu.
And while it doesn’t look like much today,
the waves here are the biggest
and most dangerous in the world.
And understand that everything
about the ocean changes completely
when a wave goes over eight feet.
And here they don’t stop at eight.
They go well over 30 feet.
I’ll say that again. Thirty feet.
Does that scare you?
-No.
-It should.
When you get caught in the drop zone,
and you will get caught in drop zone,
it’s gonna feel like a three story
building dropping right on your head.
Now, each of you will have to deal
not only with big surf
and adverse conditions,
but with death, because people die here.
Lifeguards die here.
This will be an elite team.
Since every team has a weak link,
I’m going to do us all a favor.
I’m going to find the weak link
and I’m gonna send them home.
Now... if you know
that you’re the weak link,
you can do me a favor.
Quit now.
Training starts tomorrow.
Who do you think it’s gonna be?
Not me. You’ll go before I will.
Really?
I’ve never been a weak link in my life
and it’s not gonna start here.
I didn’t think it was that serious.
You can think about how serious it was
on the plane ride home.
Who’s going home? Me?
You think it’s me? Forget that.
They’ll plant my ass
before they send me home.
-So, was I a little over the top?
-I think you got their attention.
-You gonna come along?
-No. I got someone I gotta see.
Keep up the good work.
-You’re doing a good job.
-Thanks.
I don’t know if I like this guy.
What’d you know about him?
No more than you do.
You know, it just seems like he’s trying
to set all of us against one another
and Mitch would never do
something like that.
He’s a hardass, but he’s right.
There's always a weak link.
I’d rather find out during training
than later when it really counts.
So what if it’s me and I have to go home?
Are you gonna stay?
It’s not gonna be you.
You hope it’s not me, so you
don’t have to make that decision.
Of course, then if I get sent home,
you get to be here all alone with Kekoa.
Jessie, I looked at her, that’s all.
I just looked at her.
Well, I guarantee you this, JD,
I’m not the one going home.
Good. Because it’s not going
to be me, either.
Good.
Sean?
I was thinking,
ah, during all this testing,
you gonna dance with us
or just watch from the sidelines?
A little of both.
What if it turned out to be
that you’re the weak link?
Well, that’s an interesting thought,
but it’s not possible.
But it would be pretty funny.
Hysterical.
But not possible.
No.
Good.
Hey, Mitch.
There’s someone here to see you.
[Mitch laughs]
Hina!
Wow. It’s so nice to finally meet you.
This is for you.
[Rock] Feathers.
Those are for royalty.
A medallion, huh?
It’s beautiful. Thank you.
My mother made it, for saving us.
She said to tell you,
each feather lei is unique.
There is none like it.
It’s as special and unique as you are.
Well, Hina, I’m not that special.
I am just a lifeguard doing his job.
My mother said to tell you
that as long as you have this lei,
your soul will be in our keeping.
Mahalo.
Oh, don’t forget my birthday party.
You promised to come.
I promise I’ll be there.
Well...
I’ve been thanked in a lot of ways
by a lot of people...
but no one has ever promised
to keep my soul.
It’s an honor.
Welcome to Hawaii.
Thanks, bud.
[ending theme song]
Promotional consideration
provided by Hilton Hawaiian Village
on Waikiki's best beach
and Hawaiian Airlines.
Wings of the islands.