Two of Kenya's most iconic
animals are under attack.
You have people
who are targeting
to poach rhinos and elephants.
It's a battle with heartbreaking
collateral damage.
The little one...
The mother was killed
by poachers.
As poachers become
more sophisticated,
those protecting
the animals turn hi-tech.
It's pointing right at us.
It's a dangerous job.
You are following
somebody who is armed.
If he see you he
will just shoot you.
It's another busy week
for the staff
at Lewa Wildlife Conservancy.
KENYA WILDLIFE DIARIES
THE PRICE OF IVORY IS
LIFE IMPRISONMENT
KENYA WILDLIFE DIARIES
For almost 30 years -
this has been a rare sight here
on the slopes of Mt. Kenya.
But today it is
becoming more common.
Africa is once again
at war with poachers.
You have people who are
targeting to poach
rhinos and elephants,
and these are the people
we're fighting with.
That's a huge, huge challenge to us.
It's a dangerous job.
You are following somebody
who is armed with an AK-47
and you know definitely that person,
if he sees you, will just shoot you.
Elephant and rhino have walked
the earth for nearly 50 million years.
Now they are in urgent danger.
In less than the lifespan
of a single animal,
both have been pushed
to the brink of extinction
by another species... humans.
In effect, we are at war
with ourselves for their survival.
In the last poaching crisis
in the 1980's,
80% of the elephants
and 90% of the rhinos
were brutally slaughtered.
The elephants - for their ivory,
which was used
in decorative carvings.
The rhino for their horn,
used in traditional
Asian medicines.
It took aggressive
anti-poaching action,
bolstered by a worldwide ban
on the sale of both ivory and rhino horn
to bring an end to the slaughter.
But a renewed global black market
has once again
put Africa on the front lines.
When you are talking
of rhino poaching,
that is a syndicate.
You have main dealers
and you have the brokers between.
And then you have the gunmen,
the people on the ground.
Those are the people who
can kill these animals.
They are poor people.
They are people who are being killed.
So what I can just tell the poachers:
don't risk yourself,
because we will bring
all the technology we can bring
to stop the poaching.
This is where Kenya's Lewa
Conservancy comes into play.
Sitting in the shadow of Mt. Kenya,
it covers a modest area,
just twice the size of Paris,
Lewa is dedicated to protecting
critically endangered animals.
To ensure the rhino
and elephant's safety,
the conservancy is fenced
in on several sides.
On the front lines of the fight
is Lewa's team of armed rangers
who put their lives on the line
to ensure these species
don't disappear on their watch.
The team at Lewa knows
that the battle against poaching
can't just be fought on the front lines
as an armed conflict.
The only way
these animals will survive
is to change the perception
of ordinary people
on a global scale
that these animals deserve
a safe and free place in the wild.
If they fail,
these animals will go extinct.
This rhino was shot dead
by someone in our village.
Our main question is
are we happy to see skeletons,
skeletons of animals?
Or are we happy to see animals
feeding, suckling their young ones.
That is my question.
A single gunshot from a poacher
has enormous ramifications.
When a mother is killed,
the babies are left alive.
In the wild
they are extremely vulnerable,
unable to take care of themselves,
and will quickly die or be killed.
However, orphaned animals
from all over Kenya
get a second chance at Lewa.
This one 23 months,
and this one 17 months,
and all boys.
The little one,
their mothers were
killed by poachers.
Few conservancies have the capabilities,
or the resources to care for them.
It is a labour intensive,
expensive long term commitment.
Lewa has caregivers who look after
and protect these young rhinos
24 hours a day.
The rhinos are
assigned a caregiver.
The young rhino
imprint on the rangers,
who effectively become
their surrogate mothers.
They will teach them the skills
they need to become wild rhinos again.
It's ironic that their lives
now depend on the species
that put them
in this predicament.
We walk them around
1km every day.
Their day mimics life in the wild.
Getting used to the new terrain
and covering important tasks
like personal hygiene.
The climate is getting hot now.
So the rhinos are going
to have a mud bath.
We actually have to take them
once a day.
Rhinos, they don't have sweat glands,
so they cool
their body temperatures down,
and also there are
some parasites like ticks
so when they cover
their body by the mud
and later on
they just rub against the tree
to remove the ticks off.
Kilif and Hope you can
release after 4 to 5 years.
Raising a rhino here
at Lewa is a balancing act.
These are not pets.
Keeping baby rhinos tame
to protect them is not a solution.
It requires tremendous resources
to keep a captive animal,
especially ones that can
live into their forties.
And it's imperative
they be returned to the wild
to enrich the gene pool.
The rangers know they
will be releasing their little charges
into a world fraught with dangers.
And that includes
danger from poachers.
It's frustrating to them.
Poaching is a human problem,
and it has to be stopped by humans.
Lewa's successful rhino program
is great news for conservation efforts.
But it's put
the conservancy and its staff
into a much more dangerous situation.
When I started here in terms
of rhinos that was less than 20.
As we speak today
we have 135 rhinos.
There have been a lot of challenges
moving from security-wise
from less
than 20 security to 150 security.
Okay, Sawa Charlie,
we are coming back.
The rangers are armed
with military grade weapons,
but anti poaching at Lewa
is not an offensive tool.
It's meant to deter poachers
and especially locals
who are often recruited by gangs
with the promise of a big pay day
that could be more money
that they'd see in a year.
So when head ranger John Pamori
is looking for new rangers,
he looks to the local communities
In terms of recruitment in Lewa,
when we are recruiting people
we target the communities around here.
A steady job and a solid income
can mean one less person tempted
by the poaching money
and one more convert to seeing
healthy rhino and elephant populations
as a resource for the community,
worth protecting.
In Kenya, wildlife
conservancies, like Lewa,
have one central mission:
to provide a safe habitat
for the world's most vulnerable
and endangered creatures.
And now, they are dealing
with their most serious challenge.
With demand for illegal
ivory and rhino horn
skyrocketing in Asia
poaching is at its worst
level in over thirty years.
The government of Kenya
is taking this crisis very seriously.
It has imposed stiff penalties
for wildlife crimes.
The government works
closely with Lewa
and several other conservancies
in the region.
They have partnered up to create
an elite rapid response team.
The team is capable of dealing
with the growing threat,
not just to the conservancy
but all across northern Kenya.
It is well armed, well trained
and very well equipped.
The goal for this elite unit
is not to engage and destroy
the enemy on the front lines
in an all out war.
The hope is
that through a show of force,
they can deter
poachers completely.
But all the arms in the world
can't beat basic economics.
Ounce for ounce,
rhino horn is worth more than gold
in the underground market.
In a country where
poverty is a major issue
poaching pays 6 months salary
for a single day's work.
All you need is a gun
and an opportunity.
There are many people
who are willing to risk their lives
for that equation.
With severe penalties
for poaching rhino or elephants
the poachers
are desperate not to get caught.
They won't hesitate to kill a ranger,
and that desperation
adds another level of danger.
We have different firearms here.
This one is from the government,
being issued to our armed teams.
The Elite team members
don't have backgrounds in the military.
But they have outside partners
who provide regular training.
The Kenyan government
has accepted help
from the British Forces,
who have sent experts
to help train the rangers
on advanced engagement
and capture techniques.
Tonight's exercise
will include the latest in aerial
and ground technology.
The poaching gangs
are becoming ever more sophisticated
with the money that's involved in it.
Through the 90's there was
a relatively quiet period.
That now has
escalated dramatically
because of the escalation
in the price of rhino horn
in the Far East
and the demand there.
So it's been
about as bad as its ever been
these last four, five years.
Let's just bring the scope back a bit.
We'll head off that way
and then cut back this way.
Happy hunting!
Watch your feet.
Sam, a training specialist,
leads a small team,
playing the role of poachers.
They'll emulate the real thing:
skilled, fast and difficult to catch.
The poachers appear to be
incredibly fast at getting a horn off,
which is why
this training is so important.
It's hopefully keeping us
one step ahead of the game.
In this exercise the poaching team
stays put as long as it would take
for a poacher to cut off a rhino horn.
And what we're going to do
is fire off a few shots
as though we were cutting off a horn
and then move out as though unaware
that we had been located.
Okay, go.
There's the various scenes here...
they'll try to pinpoint it,
and now they're in the process
of setting up ambushes.
Okay,
we're going to start moving west now.
Okay guys, we're going to move on.
Once a shot is fired,
it will take an average
of about 40 minutes
to escape the conservancy.
An eternity for the poacher...
the blink of an eye for the ranger team.
Cameraman you follow him.
We're just carrying on...
heading to the north.
They look for cover.
But the point of this exercise
is to provide no place to hide.
Okay, guys.
They got the laser on us now.
The use of the chopper
provides a strong advantage.
It can pinpoint the enemy,
follow them,
and communicate
their position to the ground crew.
They're pointing
right at us.
So the guys can see a beam
from further away.
With an aircraft, they can
push the poachers to an ambush
making it easier for the rangers
on the ground to nab them.
As a bonus,
the shock and awe factor
sends a clear signal for miles,
Lewa's defences are active.
Okay.
Are we dead?
The poachers
in this exercise are taken alive,
which is an important tactic.
If one of the poachers is killed,
then another one
will simply take his place.
But if taken alive
they could lead
the investigation to the middlemen.
I got a blank right in the ear.
They did really well.
Good. Well organized.
If under pressure,
poachers have two options.
Make a run for it,
or wait and hide.
If they choose to hide
even a helicopter may
not be able to find them.
For that scenario Lewa
also has a less high tech solution.
We have
these two bloodhounds here.
They assist
in tracking poachers.
In the course of their duties
they work in pack environments.
Like their human counterparts,
these dogs require constant
honing of their skills.
Today we are doing
an exercise with tracker dogs.
We are going to send
a poacher first.
Then we are going to track
and also test the dogs.
Yeah, every day you have
to use a new person,
because you know for the dogs
it has to be get used
to a different scent.
Because if you use
the same person for every day
it will be the same scent.
Now we are putting the harness on,
the dog will realize
it's working time now.
Bloodhounds were originally bred
as deer hunting dogs,
but they are
equally apt at tracking humans.
With 200 million olfactory receptors,
compared to 5 million for humans,
these dogs are built
for one specific task,
and they don't disappoint.
As part of the exercise,
a scouting plane
will try to provoke the poachers.
If anyone gets in their way,
poachers often make
the mistake of firing their weapons,
in an attempt to intimidate.
But this only draws the dogs in,
and then it's just a matter of time.
These "poachers" can walk away.
But Lewa's most valuable
domestic species
is ready for the real thing.
It's another busy day
at Kenya's Lewa Conservancy.
In this current climate
of aggressive poaching,
rangers constantly
monitor the welfare
of all the conservancy's
endangered animals.
A report has come
in that a young elephant
has entered the conservancy
with a wire snare around it's leg.
It's of great concern
to head Ranger Chilimo.
He has called in the Kenyan
Wildlife Service Mobile Vet Unit
based at Lewa.
This elephant is lucky
that it was spotted by rangers.
If it had not walked
into the conservancy,
and right past the rangers,
it is likely the snare
would not have been reported.
The wire would have dug
into the elephant's leg
creating a painful infection.
Untreated the young elephant
would have died
an agonizing death.
The drug won't put
the animal to sleep,
it will just immobilize it
so the team can work safely.
The team is lucky.
Even though
these elephants are wild,
they're habituated
and don't mind the vehicles.
So we are just preparing a dart,
to immobilize an elephant
to remove a snare
on its right hind foot.
We have to remove it because it's-
it will tighten as it goes along,
and it can even cause
very serious wounds.
The vet team begins
to push the mother off.
The risk to the team is enormous
nothing is more dangerous
then getting
between a wild elephant and her baby.
The elephant is now down.
The mother looks on.
She is confused and agitated
but is holding
back at a distance.
But at any moment
her instincts could kick in
and she could charge the team.
They are just
about 200 meters from us.
It remains a volatile situation.
The wire is removed.
It turns out to be a piece of fence
wrapped around the baby's leg,
and not a poacher's snare.
Its good news
but still poses
the same danger to the animal
so it was crucial it was removed.
So we are not going
keep her any longer.
The Kenyan Wildlife vet
administers the antidote.
But it's ok.
It looks stable.
I'm sure they are waiting
The little elephant
begins to come around.
After a moment
to get its orientation,
it shakes off the drug,
and goes back to it's family.
The group moves on.
Back at the Headquarters,
their elephant troubles continue.
An urgent call comes in.
The details are sketchy.
They're told that an elephant
has been shot and severely injured
in a village three hours
outside of the conservancy.
A full elite team is dispatched.
Once they're outside
the boundaries of the conservancy
all bets are off
they have to be
prepared for anything.
For Kenyan Wildlife Service
head vet Mathew Mutinda,
it's a different story.
His concern is for the animal.
We're going to investigate
and decide a course of action.
If it's a treatable case
we are going to fix it.
As they approach,
the mood gets somber.
A Kenyan Wildlife Service
ranger unit is waiting for them.
They lead Mathew
to the elephant.
This is where the elephant was shot,
it collapsed here,
and crawled to where it now lays.
This is everyone's
worst fear.
The elephant is in agony.
The guys heard a shot yesterday
and they
came to investigate the shot
and they found an elephant.
Even for Matthew and the team
who are used to seeing
animals in distress,
this is an awful experience.
Mathew
will have to make a quick decision.
The animal
is obviously suffering.
It's welfare
it's in a lot of pain
and you can clearly see where
there is an entry wound.
Sawa.
For Mathew, the decision is obvious.
It won't be a happy ending.
It's terrible.
It's terrible...
it's bad enough... it's broken.
This is really bad to happen.
Unfortunately we have to put it down,
but we can't show it on camera.
It's got to be done
with respect for the animal,
and now we have to request
that you guys have to leave
so that we can do that.
For Chilimo this is a terrible irony
he came here to save an animal
but will now have to kill
one to end it's suffering.
However before he does.
The animal succumbs to its injuries.
The rangers see death
of animals on a regular basis.
But this does not make
this any easier for them.
They take the loss to heart.
With the agony of the animal over,
the job now shifts to an investigation.
Rangers learn the shooter
is from the community
and they want to question him.
The death of an elephant is
taken very seriously in Kenya.
If this is poaching the shooter
could face life in prison.
Unfortunately there is more bad news
the team from Lewa learns
the elephant had a young baby.
In the hours after the mother was shot,
the baby was left
unprotected and vulnerable.
It was killed and eaten
by hyenas this morning.
It's tragic to think
that although gravely wounded,
she managed
to outlive her baby.
In a wildlife conservancy
like Kenya's Lewa,
there are a lot of good days
when efforts to protect
endangered wildlife
are rewarded by the beautiful
quiet of an African plain.
But today has not been
one of those days.
I was ready to euthanize the animal
because it was
in pain on welfare grounds
but before I did
that the animal died.
Even for the veterans,
this was a tough one.
Now it's time to get
to the bottom of what happened.
Penalties for poaching
in Kenya are severe.
In this case the shooter is
not denying he shot the animal,
but claims it was self-defence.
It's hard to say
until you do a postmortem
and retrieve the bullet.
It's tough to know
what his intentions were.
The facts are that several
community members
responded to the gun shot,
and reported it authorities.
But the shooter did not make
any attempt to report it himself.
So they're left with the question
Is the shooter telling the truth
or did he simply come
across an elephant
and decide to take advantage.
The rangers fear
this opportunistic shooting
represents a growing trend
in poaching in Kenya.
These one-off shooters know
they can access low level brokers
who then supply
more organized poaching rings
to move the ivory out.
Each town you have a broker
they are people just sitting
waiting to be delivered.
If they get caught,
the penalty means serious jail time.
But still some feel
that the financial windfall
is worth the risk.
Most of the time it's
so difficult to get.
In terms of arresting somebody,
you might not be able
to arrest someone red handed.
If they are not
caught in the act,
they can return under the cover
of darkness to remove the tusks.
Unfortunately this is
not a clear cut case,
and will likely take months
to go through the courts.
Tighten, tighten, tighten
KWS vet Mathew Mutinda
is about to carry out a forensic
post-mortem on the animal.
The bullet needs to be retrieved
to make sure it corroborates
with the shooter's story,
and matches the weapon used.
If not, there could be others involved.
In the process
of doing a post-mortem
I was able to retrieve the projectile.
We do not have any indication
where the bullet would have come from,
and investigations
are going to go on.
The rangers now must face
the grim task of removing the tusks.
Unlike de-tusking
where a section of the tusk is removed,
here the tusks, which extend deep
into the skull, must be cut out.
The ivory will be sent to Nairobi
where it will be placed
in an ivory strong room.
What will happen to them
long-term is unknown.
Kenya has a history
of burning illegal ivory,
but with stockpiles being
worth millions of dollars
some countries are
hesitant to destroy them.
There is some debate that governments
should sell these as legal ivory,
cutting down the illegal
black market trade
and sending the profits
back into conservation.
The elephant carcass will
be left where it fell.
It is likely the community
will return to retrieve the meat.
The rest will be left to scavengers.
This experience points
to another important element
in the ongoing fight
to protect wildlife:
Convincing people
who have so little,
that wildlife is worth far
more to them alive, than dead.
As part of its mission Lewa is
working with the local people
to get them to see wildlife
and particularly the dollars
that come from tourism
as an asset.
It starts in the schools.
We have some animals never seen
and they wish to see today.
Tell me the difference
between a black and white rhino.
These students rarely see
or interact with wild animals
like elephant or rhino,
so they have
no connection to the species
Lewa is working
to change that.
Is this one a black or white rhino?
White rhino.
We are seeing that white rhino
have a really big mouth,
a very big head.
The world has very few rhinos,
and rhinos are being killed
by human beings in search of...
in search of their horns.
How can we protect the animals?
Is there anything that we can do?
Most of the people
who kill the animals,
do they come from China to Lewa?
The people who kill
come from our neighbourhood
so we need to inform them,
we need to teach them,
we also need to report.
(speaking local language)
CONSERVATION EDUCATION CENTRE
Who can guess
which animal is this?
Rhino. Very good.
This is rhino skeleton,
and we assembled the skeleton.
It was shot dead
by someone within our village.
And, our main question is,
are we happy to see skeletons,
skeletons of animals?
Or are we happy to see animals
feeding, suckling their young ones.
That is my question.
Education is just one piece
of reaching out to the community
and showing the benefits
of conservation.
All of us have touched
computers today,
but not every child
or every school in this country
have an access to the computer,
and therefore the computers
that we have today
is all gotten from the animals
that we are seeing today.
At the nearby Kilimani school,
Lewa's assistance
has made a major difference.
Before the intervention of Lewa
there was almost nothing.
There were old structures,
there was nothing good in place.
We were not secure.
We feel as if the classrooms
are going to fall on us.
Lewa did great things for us.
They started with our toilets
and the school fence.
The standard of hygiene
has been improved.
Minor elements like skin rashes
almost eradicated in our school.
We appreciate it is
because of wild animals
we are given these
beautiful facilities.
This has improved
the life of this community,
the life of my children.
WILDLIFE PROTECTION
AND ENVIRONMENTAL CONSERVATION
IS OUR PRIORITY
LEWA CLINIC
On site healthcare
is another cornerstone
of helping local people
connect the dots.
If their lives are good
it gives them the reasons
to avoid the lure
of the poachers money.
AMBULANCE
We are here
to offer medical services
and do the duomi
to the young children.
Lewa sponsors this program
for giving the community
medical services.
It's very helpful
for us to come to them
because for them
to walk to the district hospital,
is 59 kilometres away from this place.
Yes, it's very far away.
Every Friday we make sure we
go to at least one village.
To offer them the outreach services,
we have revealed
for them medical services.
In the case we can't manage
we take them in ambulance
either to Lepara or Lewa.
For the rangers of Lewa
the renewed poaching crisis
is just a small part of their job.
The rest of their time
it is rather routine
spent on the conservancy grounds,
tracking and monitoring
the ever growing rhino population
Under their care,
the rhino population is thriving.
Since it's inception in 1983,
Lewa's rhinos have grown
from a handful to about 140 animals.
The program has been so successful
that Lewa has been able to contribute
more than thirty rhinos
to other conservancies
for their breeding programs.
And now they have
a new addition to the rhino family.
A 28 day old male baby black rhino.
This boy was abandoned
by her mother.
So she abandoned
him overnight.
They studied the baby until morning.
The guys, the ranger team
came with him to the boma.
Elias is one of 4 rangers
who will share the duties
of being the new rhino's
surrogate mother.
This little guy is like my kid.
When I go back to my village
I talk about the baby rhinos,
how I stay there during
the day, overnight.
So I give stories.
They think it's,
they say its a very funny story.
They will guide this little charge
through the first
five years of its life.
Their goal is to teach him enough
so he can become a wild rhino again.
They will have help.
Kalifi, this little rhino's
biological brother is here.
He too was abandoned
shortly after birth
and has been under
the care of the rangers.
The baby imprinted
over the first few days
and now accepts the rangers
as its surrogate mother.
He remains close
by their side 24 hours a day.
Raising a baby rhino
is a big commitment.
It's a lot like raising
a human child.
The rangers are up early,
to make breakfast
before waking up their charges.
In the wild a baby rhino
will stay close to his mother
for the first three years.
And so the rangers
simulate that.
LWC CAPTURE
These rangers will be
with this little guy
for the next five years.
For this short while
the rangers will sleep beside the rhino
in this specially prepared shelter
so they can be sure
the baby stays safe and dry.
It will stay there for the first six
or eight months of its life
until its big enough
to join the other young rhinos.
And they'll be together
until the rhino is about five,
when it is ready to be
introduced back into the wild.
Like his brother, he will need to learn
everything from the rangers,
A wild male rhino has to know
how to mark his territory and defend it.
So the lessons
for that skill start right away.
Rhinos also need to be taught
how to care for themselves.
Their tough skin attracts tics
and so this little
guy needs to be taught
the value of a good mud bath
and other grooming routines.
At night the rangers
bring the young rhinos
back to the enclosure
for another round of hand feeding.
At just one month,
this little rhino is
still very dependent
and so,
it's back to the sleeping structure
with one of the rangers
for a cozy sleep.
For the rangers caring
for these little rhinos
it's a 24 hour a day job.
And that reflects
the level of commitment
that all of Lewa's
rangers bring to their job
of protecting wildlife.
While they see the worst
deaths from illegal poaching,
this part of their work,
is a reminder of the real joy
that comes from this deep connection
with this incredible species.
And it underlines the need
for all the work that goes on at Lewa.
Whether it's
conducting research
to make sure the range
for these animals is protected,
to fostering community
support for wildlife
through education,
medical care and job creation,
the staff at Lewa
have had real successes so far.
But there is still
much more that needs to be done.
And for the rangers who do everything
from becoming surrogate mothers
to performing like a small military
in the face of renewed rampant poaching
the work doesn't stop.
At Lewa protecting
wildlife is not just a job.
It's a way of life.
When I see like 20 rhinos
and today I see that 5 rhinos,
and I know definitely we can
make it a thousand of rhinos,
we can make it a hundred
thousand of rhinos in this country.
So I'm just warning
the people, the poachers
to stop poaching
and we can turn this country
to become something
better than today.
But if they don't do that,
we are there to fight with them.